In segment 1.1 we're going to talk
about cryptographic hash functions.
We'll talk about what they are,
and what their properties are.
And then later we'll move on and
talk about what their applications are.
So, a cryptographic hash function
is a mathematical function.
And it has three attributes
that we need to start with.
First of all,
a hash function can take any string as
input, absolutely any string of any size.
It produces a fixed-size output,
we'll use a 256 bits in this series of
lectures, cuz that's what bitcoin does.
And it has to be efficiently computable,
meaning given a string,
in a reasonable length of time,
you can figure out what the output is.
So that's a hash function, but
we're going to need hash functions
that are cryptographically secure.
The cryptographic properties of
hash functions are a complicated
topic in general.
But we're gonna focus here on
three particular properties.
And I'll explain in
a minute what those are.
In particular,
that the function is collision-free,
that it has a hiding property,
and that it's puzzle-friendly.
And for each of these, I'll talk about
what the property is, what it means.
And then I'll talk about why it's useful
to have a function that has that property.
So, first, collision-free.
So, the first property that we need
from a cryptographic hash function
is that it's collision free.
And what that means is that it's
impossible, nobody can find values x and
y, such that x and
y are different, and yet
the hash of x is equal to the hash of y.
And so if we look at the operation
of the function as depicted
by one of these red arrows.
Here's x and H(x), and here's y and H(y).
Then nobody can find
a situation like this.
That you have an x and y that
are separate, and yet when you hash them,
they hash to the same value.
Now one thing to notice is that I said,
nobody can find.
I didn't say that there is no collision,
because if you think about it
there has to be a collision.
Collisions do exist, and to understand
why that is, we can use this diagram.
Over here on the left, I'm depicting all
of the possible inputs to this function,
which can be a string of any size.
And over here,
I have all of the possible outputs,
which has to be string
of 256 bits in size.
So the right hand side here, the outputs,
there are only 2 to the 256 possibilities.
Over here, there are more possibilities.
And so if you think that every
point here on the left is gonna
be mapped by an arrow,
to some point on the right.
You can see that as you go from all
the points over here on the left into
the right, it has to get crowded.
And in fact,
that there have to be multiple
values over here on the left that
map to the same output over here.
In fact, in general, there will be
a very large number of possible inputs
that map to any particular output.
So collisions do exist.
I said before nobody can find a collision.
And that's the key question.
We know collisions exist.
The question is are there any collisions
that are findable by regular people
using regular computers?
Okay, now to make things even worse,
I said that it has to be
impossible to find a collision.
Let me tell you how to find a collision,
because there's a method
that's guaranteed to work.
And the method works like this.
That we're gonna pick 2 to
the 130 randomly chosen inputs,
over on the left cloud of
that previous diagram.
And if we pick those 2 to
the 130 randomly chosen inputs,
it turns out there's a 99.8% chance that
at least two of them are going to collide.
And so this is a simple method for
finding a collision.
It works no matter what the hash function
is, but of course, the problem is,
that this takes a very,
very long time to do.
You have to compute the hash
function 2 to the 130 times.
And that's, of course,
an astronomical number.
This method works no matter
which hash function we're using.
There's still a 99.8%
probability that this works.
And if it doesn't work, just try it again,
it'll probably work the next time.
But, this doesn't really matter.
And the reason it doesn't really matter,
is that this procedure takes 2 to
the 130 steps,
in order to get to that high probability.
So, we can say something like this.
We can say that if every
computer ever made by humanity
was computing since the beginning
of the entire Universe up to now,
the odds that they would have found a
collision is still infinitesimally small.
So small that it's way less than the odds
that the Earth will be destroyed by
a giant meteor in the next two seconds,
which didn't happen.
Okay, so we know how to find a collision.
But this method takes too long to matter.
The question is, is there some other
method that could be used on a particular
hash function,
in order to find a collision?
And that's the question
that is harder to answer.
Is there a faster way to find collisions?
Well, for some possible values of
hash functions, of course there are.
For example, if our hash function
were to simply take the input,
modulo 2 to the 256, that is, it just
selected the last 256 bits of the input.
Then we would know an easy
way to find a collision.
One collision would be the values 3,
and 3 plus 2 to the 256.
So, for
some possible values of the hash function,
it's very easy to find a collision.
For others, we don't know.
Now, one thing I need to note
is that there's no hash function
in existence which has been
proven to be collision free.
There are just some that people have tried
really, really hard to find collisions and
haven't succeeded.
And so we choose to believe
that those are collision free.
Okay, now,
what good does collision freedom do us?
If we can assume that we have a hash
function that is collision free,
then we can use that hash
function as message digest.
And what I mean by that is the following.
That if we know that x and
y have the same hash,
then it's safe to assume that x and
y are the same.
Because if someone knew an x and y that
were different, that had the same hash,
of course, that would be a collision.
Since there's not a collision that we know
of, then knowing the hashes are the same,
we can assume that
the values are the same.
And this let's us use the hash
as a kind of message digest.
Suppose, for example,
that we had a file, a really big file.
And we wanted to be able to recognize
later whether another file was the same
as the file we saw the first time, right?
So one way to do that would be
to save the whole big file.
And then when we saw another file later,
just compare them.
But because we have hashes that
we believe are collision free,
it's more efficient to just remember
the hash of the original file.
Then if someone shows us a new file,
and claims that it's the same,
we can compute the hash of that
new file and compare the hashes.
If the hashes are the same,
then we conclude that the files
must have been the same.
And that gives us a very efficient way
to remember things we've seen before and
recognize them again.
And, of course,
this is useful because the hash is small,
it's only 256 bits, while the original
file might be really big.
So hash is useful as a message digest.
And we'll see, later on in this lecture,
and in subsequent lectures,
why it's useful to use
hash as a message digest.
So, the second property that we want from
our hash function is that it's hiding.
And the property that we
want is something like this.
That if we're given the output
of the hash function,
that there's no feasible way to
figure out what the input x was.
The problem is that this
property doesn't exactly hold.
And to understand why that's the case,
let's look at this example.
So here, what we're going to do is
an experiment where we flip a coin.
And if the result of
the coin flip was heads,
we're going to return the hash
of the string "heads".
And if the result was tails, we're going
to return the hash of the string "tails".
And now we're gonna ask someone
who didn't see the coin flip, but
only saw this hash output, to figure out
what the string was that was hashed.
That, of course, is going to be easy.
It's easy in this scenario to find what
the input string was, it's easy to find x.
You simply compute the hash
of the string "heads" and
the hash of the string "tails",
and you see which one you got.
And so, in just a couple of steps,
you can figure out what x was.
So the reason this example failed,
that is the reason why an adversary
was able to guess what the string was,
was that there were only
a couple of possible values of x.
And so, if we're gonna have
a hiding property like this,
it needs to be the case that there's no
value of x which is particularly likely.
That is, x has to be chosen from a set
that's, in some sense, very spread out.
So that this method for the adversary of
just trying all the possible values of x,
or just trying few values of x that are
especially likely, is not going to work.
So the hiding property that we
are going to need to set up
is a little bit more complicated.
And the way we're gonna fix this problem
with the common value x, like heads and
tails, is we're gonna take the x.
And we're gonna put next to it, we're
gonna concatenate with it, a value, r,
which is chosen from a distribution
that's really spread out.
And so this H(r | x),
that means take all the bits of r,
and put after them all the bits of x.
And so what we're going to say is
given the hash of r together with x,
that it's infeasible to find x.
And that this will be true in
the formally stated property that,
if r is a random value chosen from
a distribution that has high min-entropy,
then, given H(r | x),
it's infeasible to find x.
And what does high min-entropy mean?
Well, it captures this intuitive idea that
r is chosen from a distribution that's
really spread out.
And what that means specifically is that
there is no particular value that r could
have had, that would occur with
more than a negligible probability.
So, for example, if r is chosen uniformly
from among all of the strings that are 256
bits long, then any particular string was
chosen with probability 1 in 2 to the 256,
which is truly a negligible value.
So, as long as r was chosen that way,
then the hash of r concatenated
with x is going to hide x.
And that's the hiding property that
the hash function will be deemed to have.
Okay, now let's look at an application
of that hiding property.
And, in particular, what we wanna do
is something called a commitment.
And this is kind of the digital analogy
of taking a value, a number, and
sealing it in an envelope, and
putting that envelope out on the table,
where everyone can see it.
Now, when you do that, you've
committed to what's in the envelope.
But you haven't opened it,
it's secret from everyone else.
Later, you can open the envelope and
get out the value, but it's sealed.
So commit to a value and reveal it later.
We wanna do that in a digital sense.
So, to be more specific about what is
the API that we're going to provide here,
the commitment API looks like this,
that there are two things you can do.
First, you can commit to a message.
And that's going to return two values,
a commitment and a key.
Think of the commitment as the envelope
that you're gonna put on the table, and
the key as a secret key for
unlocking the envelope.
Then later, you allow someone else
to verify, given the commitment and
given a key, which you've told them
in the meantime, and the message.
So they can verify that that commitment,
key, and message really do go together.
And this will return a true or false.
Okay, now to seal an msg in an envelope,
what we do is we commit to the message.
And that returns a commitment and a key,
and then we publish the commitment.
That's putting the envelope on the table.
Now, later, to open the envelope, what
we're going to do is publish the key and
the message that we committed to.
And then anybody can use this verify call,
with the commitment that we
published previously, the key and
message that we just announced, to check
the validity of our opening the envelope.
Okay, and the property,
of course, we want from this,
is that it behaves like
sealing an envelope.
And, in particular,
the two security properties are these.
First, given com, the commitment,
the envelope on the table,
that someone just looking at the envelope
can't figure out what the message is.
The second property is that it's binding,
that when you commit
to what's in the envelope,
you can't change your mind later.
That is, it's infeasible to
find two different messages,
such that you can commit to one message,
and
then later claim that you committed to
another, and the whole thing will verify.
Okay, so how do we know that
these two properties hold?
Well, first we need to talk about
how we're actually gonna implement
commitments.
And the way we're gonna implement
commitments is like this.
That in order to commit
to a value message,
we're going to generate a random
256 bit value and call it the key.
And then we're going to,
as the commitment,
return the hash of the key concatenated
together with the message.
And as the key value,
we're going to return H of this key.
And then later, to verify, someone is
going to compute this same hash of
the key they were given,
concatenated with the message.
And they're gonna check whether
that's equal to the commitment that
they saw, okay?
So this is a way of using hash
functions of both in the commitment and
in the verification.
So now the security properties.
If we go down to the security properties
that were at the bottom of the previous
slide, and we just plug in the definitions
of how we're going to implement this here.
That is, this used to say com,
given com infeasible to find msg,
we just plug in what com is.
Com is the hash of key
concatenated with msg.
And similarly down here,
this is what happens when we take
what was written there before and
plug in the definition of verify in com.
Okay, so now what these properties become,
the first one is given H(key | msg),
it's infeasible to find msg.
Well, it turns out that that's
exactly the hiding property
that we talked about before.
Key was chosen random 256-bit value.
And therefore, the hiding property
says that if we take the message, and
we put before it something that was chosen
from a very spread out distribution,
like I said a random 256-bit value,
then it's infeasible to find the message.
So this is exactly the hiding property.
And this one down here turns out to be
exactly the collision-free property.
So that if someone can find two messages
which have the same hash like this,
well then they have
an input value here and
an input value there that are different,
and yet those have the same hash.
And so because of the two security
properties we've talked about for
hashes so far,
this commitment scheme will work,
in the sense that it will have
the necessary security properties.
Okay, so that's the second security
property of hashes, that they're hiding.
And the application of
that is commitments.
The third security property we're going
to need is that they're puzzle-friendly.
And this is, again,
a little bit more complicated,
but let me just go through it bit by bit.
That for any possible output value y that
you might want from the hash function.
We're going to use y as an output
value of the hash later.
That if k is chosen from a distribution
that has high min-entropy.
That is, k is chosen randomly from
some set that's super spread out.
Then there's no way to find an x, such
that the hash of k and x is equal to y.
So, what this means is basically that if
someone wants to target the hash function,
if they want it to come out to
some particular output value y.
That if there's part of the input that
is chosen in a suitably randomized way,
that it's very difficult to find another
value that hits exactly that target.
So the application we're
going to use of this,
is we're going to build a search puzzle.
And what that means is we're going
to build a mathematical problem,
which requires searching a very large
space in order to find the solution.
And where there's no shortcuts,
a way to find a good solution,
other than searching that large space.
That's a search puzzle.
To be more specific, the idea is
that if we're given a puzzle ID,
which is chosen from some high
min-entropy distribution.
That is some very spread out
probability distribution.
And we're given a target set, Y,
which someone wants to make
the hash function fall into.
Then we wanna try to find a solution, x.
So that if we hash the puzzle
ID together with the solution X,
we get a result that's in the set Y.
So the idea is Y is a target range or
a set of hash results that we want.
ID specifies a particular puzzle,
and x is a solution to the puzzle.
And the puzzle-friendly property here
implies that there's no solving strategy
for this puzzle, which is much better
than just trying random values of x.
And so if we wanna pose a puzzle
that's difficult to solve, that we can
do it this way, as long as we can generate
puzzle IDs in a suitably random way.
And we're going to use that later
when we talk about bitcoin mining.
That's the sort of computational
puzzle we're going to use.
Okay, so we've talked about three
properties of hash functions and
one application of each of those.
Now let me talk just very briefly about
the particular hash function we're going
to use.
There are lots of hash
functions in existence, but
this is the one bitcoin uses, and
it's a pretty good one to use.
It called SHA-256 or SHA-256,
and it works like this.
Basically, it takes the message
that you're hashing, and
it breaks it up into blocks
that are 512 bits in size.
The message isn't gonna be,
in general, necessarily exactly
a multiple of the block size, so we're
going to add some padding at the end.
And the padding is gonna consist of,
at the end of the padding,
a 64 bit length field, which is
the length of the message in bits.
And then before that,
it's gonna consist of a one bit,
followed by some number of zero bits.
And you choose the number of zero bits so
that this comes out exactly
to the end of a block.
So once you've padded the message so
that its length is exactly a multiple
of the 512 bit block size,
you then chop it up into blocks, and
you then execute this computation.
You start with the 256
bit value called the IV.
That's just a number that you
look up in a standards document.
And then take the IV and
the first block of the message.
You take those 768 total bits, and you
run them through this special function,
c, the compression function,
and out comes 256 bits.
You now take that with the next
512 bits of the message,
run it through c again,
and you keep going.
Each iteration of c crunches in another
512 bit block of the message and
mixes it in,
sort of logically to the result.
And when you get to the very end,
you have consumed all of the blocks
of the message plus the padding.
The result is the hash,
that's a 256 bit value.
And it's easy to show that, if this
function, c, this compression function
is collision free, then this entire hash
function will also be collision free.
The other properties are a little
bit more complicated, so
I won't talk about them here.
Okay, so we've talked hash functions.
We've talked about what hash functions do.
We've talked about three properties
of hash functions and applications of
those properties, and the specific
hash function that we use in bitcoin.
In the next lecture segment,
we'll talk about ways of
using hash functions to build
more complicated data structures that are
used in distributed systems like bitcoin.